<?xml version="1.0"?> 

<!--
	description:
	
		"Examples of using the library"

	library: "Gobo Eiffel XSLT Library"
	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2005, Colin Adams and others"
	license: "MIT License"
	date: "$Date$"
	revision: "$Revision$"
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/documentation" id="xslt_examples">
  <chapterinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
      <holder>Colin Adams and others</holder>
    </copyright>
    <author>
      <firstname>Colin</firstname>
      <surname>Adams</surname>
    </author>
    <email>colin@colina.demon.co.uk</email>
    <date>Monday, Octobber 10th, 2005</date>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>Examples of using the library</title>
  <para>
    This chapter deals with examples of how to invoke XSLT transformations
    from within your Eiffel programs. It does not cover writing XSLT programs. For that
    you should look elsewhere (a good starting point is the <ulink url="http://www.dpawson.co.uk/xsl/xslfaq.html">XSLT FAQ</ulink>).
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>A Schematron validator</title>
    <para>
      In $GOBO/examples/xml/xslt/schematron , there is a complete example of using the
      library. This is a command-line validator using the Schematron language. See the readme.txt
      file for instructions on compiling and using the program.
    </para>
    <para>
      The creation procedure <featurename>make</featurename> starts by creating a configuration,
      and then it sets the recovery policy to recover from recoverable errors without writing
      any error messages. Because the program uses Eiffel <classname>STRING</classname>s for the
      result of a transformation (and also for the source of a stylesheet), it next goes on
      to create a <classname>XM_STRING_URI_RESOLVER</classname>, so that the XML parser can
      locate the <classname>STRING</classname>s involved.
    </para>
    <para>
      After processing the command line arguments, it then performs the first stage - a transformation
      of a Schematron rules file (a schema) into a stylesheet (which will be used to perform the 
      actual validation). This is performed by <featurename>transform_schematron_rules</featurename>. This is fairly
      straightforward. The only thing of particular note is that the resulting <classname>STRING</classname> has
      to be plugged into the resolver, as the XML parser needs to find it in the next stage of the program
    </para>
    <para>
      At this point, we have the result of <featurename>transform_schematron_rules</featurename> in a
      <classname>STRING</classname>. Interestingly, the contents of this <classname>STRING</classname> is
      another XSLT stylesheet. We now go on to use this stylesheet to perform a transformation against the
      file which is to be validated. This is done in <featurename>create_report</featurename>. The interesting code
      in this case arises if the user has requested output to a file, rather than standard output. Notice that although
      the program takes filenames (for the convenience of the user), the <featurename>transform</featurename> feature
      of <classname>XM_XSLT_TRANSFORMER</classname> takes arguments that require URIs for their creation procedures.
      This is a requirement of the XSLT specification.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Schematron validator program writes a report to standard output or to a file, if validation fails.
      If validation is successful, then no output is produced. This situation could be detected by writing the output to a
      <classname>STRING</classname> instead, and checking if it's <featurename>count</featurename> were zero (successful validation),
      or not (an error report has been produced). So if you wanted to use the XSLT library to perform Schematron validation
      from within your own programs, then this is how you would do it.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Gexslt</title>
    <para>
      The Gobo Eiffel XSLT command line processor comes close to being the ultimate
      example of how to use the XSLT library, in as much as it allows most options to be used. You can 
      see the source in $GOBO/src/gexslt/gexslt.e .
      <!-- TODO: break up the code into smaller routines to make it easier to follow. -->
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Gestalt</title>
    <para>
     Other examples are in the Gestalt distribution (see <ulink url="http://gestalt.sourceforge.net">Gestalt</ulink>).
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
