<?xml version="1.0"?> 

<!--
	description:

		"ECF Pretty-Printer"

	tool: "Gobo Eiffel Compiler"
	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2018, Eric Bezault and others"
	license: "MIT License"
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/documentation" id="gedoc/ecf_pretty_printer">
<chapterinfo>
	<copyright>
		<year>2018</year>
		<holder>Eric Bezault</holder>
	</copyright>
	<author>
		<firstname>Eric</firstname><surname>Bezault</surname>
	</author>
	<email>ericb@gobosoft.com</email>
	<date>23 October 2018</date>
</chapterinfo>

<title>ECF Pretty-Printer</title>

<para>
<projectname>gedoc</projectname> can be used as an ECF pretty-printer. The resulting
ECF file will be formatted using the same guidelines as used throughout the 
<projectname>Gobo Eiffel Project</projectname>. It can also be used to convert
an ECF file to newer versions of ECF.
</para>

<section><title>Pretty-printing an ECF file</title>
<para>
Here is how to pretty-print the ECF file <filename>project.ecf</filename>:
<programlisting>
	<filename>gedoc --force --format=ecf_pretty_print project.ecf</filename>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
The command-line option <filename>--force</filename> tells <projectname>gedoc</projectname>
to overwrite the ECF file being pretty-printed. Without this option, files will not be 
overwritten and <projectname>gedoc</projectname> will emit an error message. Alternatively,
the command-line option <filename>--interactive</filename> can be used. It will ask confirmation
to the user before overwriting files. If you want to generate the pretty-printed file in a
directory different from the one containing the original ECF file, you should use the
command-line option <filename>--output</filename>.
</para>
</section>

<section><title>Converting an ECF file</title>
<para>
Converting an ECF file to a given version of ECF is similar to pretty-printing
this ECF file, except that you have to provide the version of ECF you want
your ECF file to be converted to:
<blockquote>
	<filename>gedoc --force --format=ecf_pretty_print --ecf=1.18.0 project.ecf</filename>
</blockquote>
This will convert the ECF file <filename>project.ecf</filename> to version 1.18.0.
Alternatively, you can convert your ECF file to the last version of ECF known
by <projectname>gedoc</projectname>:
<blockquote>
	<filename>gedoc --force --format=ecf_pretty_print --ecf=latest project.ecf</filename>
</blockquote>
Note that trying to convert an ECF file to a version older than the
one initially used to write this file might end up in a loss of information.
For example some options, settings or capabilities used in your ECF file
may not be supported in older versions.
</para>
</section>
</chapter>
