<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
	description:

		"Argument Parser Introduction"

	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2006, Bernd Schoeller and others"
	license: "MIT License"
	date: "$Date$"
	revision: "$Revision$"
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/documentation" id="argument/introduction">
<chapterinfo>
	<copyright>
		<year>2001-2006</year>
		<holder>Bernd Schoeller</holder>
	</copyright>
	<author>
		<firstname>Bernd</firstname><surname>Schoeller</surname>
	</author>
	<email>bernd@fams.de</email>
	<date>14 September 2006</date>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Argument Parser Introduction</title>

<para>
	The argument library gives you the ability to parse the
	command line arguments that are passed to your application. It
	is a feature-rich library that tries to achieve the maximum
	comfort for the developer and for the user of the application
	at the same time.
</para>

<section id="arguments">

	<title>About arguments</title>

	<para>
		Arguments normally come in two different forms:
		<emphasis>options</emphasis> and
		<emphasis>parameters</emphasis>. Parameters (sometimes
		also called operands) are the main inputs to the
		program, for example the filename give to a text
		editor or the URL that a web-browser should open on
		startup.
	</para>

	<programlisting>myprog parameter1 parameter2 ... parameterX</programlisting>

	<para>
		Options - on the other hand - are normally not mandatory for
		the proper operation of the application. They are introduced
		with the - (minus) character.
	</para>

	<para>
		There are short options and there are long
		options. <emphasis>Short options</emphasis> are
		introduced by a - (a single minus) followed by a
		single character. <emphasis>Long options</emphasis>
		are introduced by -- (two minus) and the name of the
		option.
	</para>

	<programlisting>myprog -o --foo --bar=HALLO</programlisting>

	<para>
		In the given example, -o and --foo are so-called
		<emphasis>flags</emphasis> to the program. Flags are
		options that do not take any argument. The option
		--bar is an option that takes an argument, in this
		case the string HALLO.
	</para>

	<para>
		Options and parameters can be mixed together and there are
		ways to combine options. This can create creating complex
		command lines. The following is an example call of the
		<emphasis>GNU ls</emphasis> command available on most Linux
		systems:
	</para>

	<programlisting>/bin/ls -Al /tmp -I '*~' -I*.bak --color=always</programlisting>

	<para>
		Here, /tmp is the only parameter. The flags -A and -l
		have been merged into a single option. The option -I
		is set twice with the argument '*~' and '*.bak' and
		the option --color is set with the argument 'always'
		(note that the command line parser does not care
		whether the arguments to a short options are
		introduced by a space or follow directly).
	</para>
</section>

<section id="goals">

	<title>Design decisions and goals</title>

	<para>
		The main focus of a developer is to create a program
		that provides the needed functionality. Comfortable
		command line parsing is difficult. Many programmers
		regard it as dispensable and few invest the necessary
		time to get it right.
	</para>

	<para>
		As a consequence, the command line behavior of tools
		varies a lot. There are probably as many ways to parse
		the command line as there are developers writing
		applications. Often you have difficulties to use a
		tool because you wrote the command line arguments
		wrong, as the tool required them in a very specific form.
		If also a useful help text message is missing,
		the user wastes unnecessary time browsing through
		man pages and application documentation, or just uses
		trial-and-error until the command line arguments are
		OK.
	</para>

	<para>
		The <emphasis>Gobo Eiffel Argument Library</emphasis>
		tries to take the burden off the developer to bother
		himself with command line parsing. Instead, she or he
		just defines a number of options that the application
		should have, calls the parser and checks which options
		were supplied and what the applications parameters
		are.
	</para>

	<para>
		The goal is: It should be easier to parse the command
		line of the application with the library than to write
		a manual test, even if the application only has one or
		two options. Only this can motivate developers to use
		the library for their applications. At the same time,
		the library should provide a maximum in comfort for
		the user of the application, including support for
		many option styles, abbreviation facilities, and a
		useful, automatically generated help text.
	</para>

	<para>
		With this goals in mind, there are a number of
		properties that the library has, that will not satisfy
		every need for software development. Specially, the
		library imposes a certain, standard way of command
		line parsing onto the application. If you want a very
		different way of command line parsing, perhaps because
		you want to be 'backward compatible' with another
		application, the argument parsing library might not be
		the best choice for you. Also, if you have a very
		large application that requires complex argument
		patterns, then you will need a significant amount of
		extra work to parse them using this library.
	</para>

	<para>
		This being said, it is my firm belief that the library
		should be suited for most application needs. And it
		enforces a consistent behavior of different
		applications, something that your users will appreciate.
	</para>

</section>

<section id="features">

	<title>Feature overview</title>

	<para>
		To get the buzz-words right, here is a short overview
		of what you get when you are using the library.
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
			Different types of options: flags, strings, integers, booleans ...
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Long (--make-love) and short (-l) options are supported.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Short form can be joined (-abc instead of -a -b -c), assuming that
			every one but the last is a flag (does not require an argument).
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Arguments to the short form can be added with or without space
			(-ltoday or -l today).
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Arguments to the long form can be added with '=' or with a space
			(--make-love=today or --make-love today)
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Option termination introduced by '--'.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Usage instructions and a help text will be generated automatically
			from the options.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Good default values, minimal code is required for standard
			applications.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			No special 'option description language' is required. It is all just
			plain Eiffel code.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section id="strategy">

	<title>Usage strategy</title>

	<para>
		The general usage strategy of the argument parser
		library involves the following four steps:
	</para>

	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>
			Create an instance of <classname>AP_PARSER</classname> and configure
			it (for example setting up a descriptions of the application).
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Create instances of options types, that is of the classes that
			inherit from <classname>AP_OPTION</classname>. Configure these instances
			(for example with a help text for this option). Register these options
			at the parser.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			Parse the command line, most of the time by just calling
			<featurename>parse_arguments</featurename> on the parser.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
			See if options were found by calling <featurename>was_found</featurename>
			in its instances. Get the parameters (non-option arguments) from the parser
			itself by querying it for <featurename>parameters</featurename>.
		</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

</section>

<section id="example">

	<title>An example</title>

	<para>
		Lets go for an example that shows how to apply these
		four steps in practice. The example is rather lengthy,
		but it shows most of the possibilities of the library.
		The different steps in the usage strategy above have
		been marked by comments.
	</para>

	<para>
		As an example we look again at the <emphasis>GNU
		ls</emphasis> and implement command line parsing for
		only the four options we already used above.
	</para>

<programlisting>
feature -- Options and Flags

   allmost_all_flag: AP_FLAG
   long_format_flag: AP_FLAG
   color_option: AP_ENUMERATION_OPTION
   ignore_option: AP_STRING_OPTION

feature -- Main

   make is
         -- Main routine, called when the program is executed.
      local
         parser: AP_PARSER
      do
            -- STEP 1: Creation and configuration of the parser

         create parser.make
         parser.set_application_description
            ("List information about the FILEs (the current directory by default).")
         parser.set_parameters_description ("[file] ...")

            -- STEP 2: Creation and configuration of the flags

         create allmost_all_flag.make ('A',"allmost-all")
         allmost_all_flag.set_description ("do not list implied . and ..")
         parser.options.force_last (allmost_all_flag)

         create long_format_flag.make_with_short_form ('l')
         long_format_flag.set_description ("use a long listing format")
         parser.options.force_last (long_format_flag)

         create color_option.make_with_long_form ("color")
         color_option.set_description ("control whether color is used to distinguish file types.")
         color_option.extend ("never")
         color_option.extend ("always")
         color_option.extend ("auto")
         parser.options.force_last (color_option)

         create ignore_option.make ('I',"ignore")
         ignore_option.set_description ("do not list implied entries matching shell PATTERN")
         ignore_option.set_parameter_description ("PATTERN")
         parser.options.force_last (ignore_option)

            -- STEP 3: Parse the arguments

         parser.parse_arguments

            -- STEP 4: Read results

         if allmost_all_flag.was_found then
            print ("list allmost all%N")
         end
         if long_format_flag.was_found then
            print ("use long format%N")
         end
         if color_option.was_found then
            print ("use coloring "+color_option.parameter+"%N")
         end

         if ignore_option.was_found then
            from
               ignore_option.parameters.start
            until ignore_option.parameters.off loop
               print ("ignore pattern: "+
                      ignore_option.parameters.item_for_iteration+"%N")
               ignore_option.parameters.forth
            end
         end
         from
            parser.parameters.start
         until parser.parameters.off loop
            print ("parameter: "+
                   parser.parameters.item_for_iteration+"%N")
            parser.parameters.forth
         end
      end
</programlisting>

	<para>
		If we now call the application with the arguments are
		given in the example above, we get the following output:
	</para>

<programlisting>
$ ./my_ls -Al /tmp -I '*~' -I*.bak --color=always
list allmost all
use long format
use coloring always
ignore pattern: *~
ignore pattern: *.bak
parameter: /tmp
</programlisting>

	<para>
		Also, we get a full help text for free (!). See what
		happens when we call the application with '-h'.
	</para>

<programlisting>
$ ./my_ls -h
usage: ls_example [-A] [-l] [--color=never|always|auto] [-I PATTERN] [file] ...
       ls_example --help

List information about the FILEs (the current directory by default).

Options:
-A, --allmost-all             do not list implied . and ..
    --color=never|always|auto control whether color is used to distinguish
                              file types.
-h, --help                    Display this help text.
-I, --ignore=PATTERN          do not list implied entries matching shell
                              PATTERN
-l                            use a long listing format
</programlisting>

	<para>
		A second example is provided in the <classname>$GOBO/example/argument</classname>
		directory.
	</para>

</section>

</chapter>
