<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
	description:

		"About Unicode normalization"

	library: "Gobo Eiffel String Library"
	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2005, Colin Adams and others"
	license: "MIT License"
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/documentation" id="string/unicode/about">

<chapterinfo>
	<copyright>
		<year>2005</year>
		<holder>Colin Adams</holder>
	</copyright>
	<author>
		<firstname>Colin</firstname><surname>Adams</surname>
	</author>
	<email>colin-adams@users.sourceforge.net</email>
	<date>4 November 2005</date>
</chapterinfo>

<title>About Unicode normalization</title>

<para>
	Unicode normalization is all about comparing strings for equality.
</para>

<section>
<title>But I know how to compare two strings</title>
<para>
	But I already know how to compare two Unicode strings - I call 
	<featurename>STRING_.same_string</featurename> or
	<featurename>STRING_.same_case_insensitive</featurename>, so why do I need normalization?
</para>
<para>
	The problem with <featurename>STRING_.same_string</featurename> is that it compares two
	strings code-point by code-point, and assumes that if two code-points are the same, 
	then the abstract characters they represent are the same. Well, that's true enough. 
	But it also assumes that if two code-points are <emphasis>not</emphasis> the same, then
	the abstract characters that they represent are not the same. This is a reasonable assumption
	(ignoring surrogate code-points, which we can because we don't have a <classname>UC_UTF16_STRING</classname>
	yet - and when we do, <featurename>STRING_.same_string</featurename> would have to take that into 
	account when comparing a <classname>UC_UTF16_STRING</classname> with a <classname>UC_UTF8_STRING</classname>.)
</para>
<para>
	The reason this assumption fails is due to history - Unicode has been designed for round-trip
	compatibility with a number of legacy encodings, such as ISO-8859-1 (Latin-1). Latin-1 has a number of
	accented characters. One example LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A WITH GRAVE, to give it it's Unicode name, which has
	a code-point of 192.
</para>
<para>
	Other encodings enable you to compose accented characters out of a combination of a base character
	(in this case LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A at code-point 65 and COMBINING GRAVE ACCENT at code-point 768).
	Now should these two possibilites within Unicode be considered the same abstract character or not?
	In most cases, you will want to consider them the same, but <featurename>STRING_.same_string</featurename>
	will consider them to be different, and so return <featurename>False</featurename> even if the strings 
	differ in that one respect only.
</para>
<para>
	There are other characters where the situation is not so clear. What about the character 
	MATHEMATICAL BOLD CAPITAL A (code-point 119808)? Is this the same abstract character as
	LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A with just a slight presentational difference, or are they two
	distinct characters? This rather depends upon your application.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Canonical and Compatibility compositions and decompositions</title>
<para>
	Unicode answers these questions by giving you some choice in how they are answered.
	The basic idea is you convert your strings so that the same kind of representation for
	characters is used throughout, and then you can perform a binary comparison
	(with <featurename>STRING_.same_string</featurename>, for instance). This process is called 
	<emphasis role="definition">Normalization</emphasis>. But you have a choice of 
	four different ways of performing the normalization, depending upon the requirements
	of your application.
</para>
<para>
	The basic choice you have to make is whether to represent your characters using composed forms
	(such as LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A WITH GRAVE), or decomposed forms (such as LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A
	followed by COMBINING GRAVE ACCENT).
</para>
<para>
	The other choice you have to make is whether minor presentational variations such as
	MATHEMATICAL BOLD CAPITAL A versus LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A are significant or not.
	In this case, Unicode has a bias - such distinctions are assumed meaningful by default.
	That is, decompositions of this kind (MATHEMATICAL BOLD CAPITAL A decomposes to
	LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A) are labelled 
	<emphasis role="definition">Compatibility</emphasis> decompositions, whereas decompositions
	of the first kind (such as LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A WITH GRAVE decomposing to
	LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A followed by COMBINING GRAVE ACCENT) are known as 
	<emphasis role="definition">Canonical</emphasis> decompositions.
	Note that all compositions are canonical - you cannot reverse a compatibility decomposition.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>The four normalization forms</title>
<para>
	Accordingly, there are four <emphasis role="definition">Normalization forms</emphasis> defined
	in Unicode (there are additional forms defined by the 
	W3C's Character Model - see <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/charmod-norm/">Character Model for the World Wide Web 1.0: Normalization</ulink>).

	<variablelist>
 
	<varlistentry>
		<term>NFD</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>Normal Form Decomposition.</para>
		<para>This is obtained by replacing all composed characters by their canonical decompositions.</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>NFKD</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>Normal Form Kompatibility Decomposition.</para>
			<para>
				This is obtained by replacing all composed characters by their decompositions, whether
				they are canonical or compatibility decompositions.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
     
	<varlistentry>
		<term>NFC</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>Normal Form Composition.</para>
			<para>
				This is obtained by replacing all composed characters by their canonical decompositions, and then
				in turn replacing all decomposed sequences by their canonical compositions.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>NFKC</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>Normal Form Kompatibility Composition.</para>
			<para>
				This is obtained by replacing all composed characters by their decompositions (whether canonical or compatibility), and then
				in turn replacing all decomposed sequences by their canonical compositions.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
    
	</variablelist>

</para>
<para>
	NFD and NFKD tend to be longer than NFC and NFKC. Note that a pure ASCII string
	is unchanged by any of these transformations. Not so for a Latin-1 string, however.
</para>
<para>
	Since compatibility decompositions tend to equate to presentational differences, these are most
	naturally useful if you wish to do a case-insensitive comparison (since case is fundamentally a presentation
	difference in itself). Note however, that simply converting to NFKC or NFKD does not fold
	case differences. You have to further apply case folding to the resultant strings. (see TODO).
</para>
</section>
</chapter>
