<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
	description:

		"Unicode character classes"

	library: "Gobo Eiffel String Library"
	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2005, Colin Adams and others"
	license: "MIT License"
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/documentation" id="string/unicode/classes">

<chapterinfo>
	<copyright>
		<year>2005</year>
		<holder>Colin Adams</holder>
	</copyright>
	<author>
		<firstname>Colin</firstname><surname>Adams</surname>
	</author>
	<email>colin-adams@users.sourceforge.net</email>
	<date>4 November 2005</date>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Unicode character classes</title>

<section>
<title>About character classes</title>

<para>
	The <emphasis role="introduction">Unicode Character Database</emphasis> (UCD) defines 
	a character class for every code-point in Unicode.
</para>

<para>
	Within the UCD, these character classes are written as a single upper-case latin letter, to
	denote the major category, followed by a single lower-case latin letter, to denote the minor category.
	For example, if a code-point is classified as an upper case letter, then it is given the character class
	of Lu. The 'L' denotes "letter" as the major category, and the 'u' denotes "upper-case" as the minor category.
</para>

<para>
	These character classes are translated into Eiffel code as <classname>INTEGER</classname> constants in
	<classname>UC_UNICODE_CONSTANTS</classname>. The names are structured such that they start with the minor category, 
	are followed by the major category, and end with the word category. So we have <featurename>Uppercase_letter_category</featurename>,
	for instance.
</para>

<para>
	The character class for a given code-point can be retrieved by means of <featurename>character_class</featurename>
	from <classname>ST_UNICODE_CHARACTER_CLASS_INTERFACE</classname>. This can be useful for defining your own 
	classification routines. For instance, an <featurename>is_alphanumeric</featurename> routine might be 
	defined in this way (the library doesn't provide one, as more than one plausible definition is possible).
</para>

<para>
	However, some code-points can usefully be considered to be in more than one category. The UCD deals
	with this situation by defining the principle category, and also defining various character properties.
	For example, the code-points in the range 24B6..24CF (CIRCLED LATIN SMALL LETTER A..CIRCLED LATIN SMALL LETTER Z)
	are classified as So (<featurename>Other_symbol_category</featurename>). But they also have the Other_Uppercase property.
	The library handles that by providing the routine <featurename>is_upper_case</featurename>, which includes all
	code-points in <featurename>Uppercase_letter_category</featurename> and all code-points with the  Other_Uppercase property.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>How to access the character class routines provided by the library</title>

<para>
	The character class routines provided by the library are defined in the deferred class 
	<classname>ST_UNICODE_CHARACTER_CLASS_INTERFACE</classname>. In order to gain access to these routines
	you can either inherit from <classname>ST_UNICODE_CHARACTER_CLASS_ROUTINES</classname>, which
	provides information from the latest available version of unicode. Or you can inherit from a class
	for a particular version of Unicode (e.g. <classname>ST_UNICODE_V410_CHARACTER_CLASS_ROUTINES</classname> for Unicode version 4.1.0).
</para>

<para>
	Alternatively, you can access these classes as clients, by inheriting from <classname>ST_IMPORTED_UNICODE_CHARACTER_CLASS_ROUTINES</classname> 
	or <classname>ST_IMPORTED_UNICODE_V410_CHARACTER_CLASS_ROUTINES</classname>, which provide the routines
	<featurename>unicode_character_class</featurename> and <featurename>unicode_v410_character_class</featurename> respectively.
</para>

<para>
	The latter method is necessary if you want to be able to use routines from two different versions of Unicode within
	the same class.
</para>

</section>

</chapter>
