<?xml version="1.0"?> 

<!--
	description:
	
		"Extension functions"

	library: "Gobo Eiffel XSLT Library"
	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2005, Colin Adams and others"
	license: "MIT License"
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/documentation" id="xslt_output_extensions">
  <chapterinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
      <holder>Colin Adams and others</holder>
    </copyright>
    <author>
      <firstname>Colin</firstname>
      <surname>Adams</surname>
    </author>
    <email>colin@colina.demon.co.uk</email>
    <date>Monday, November 21st, 2005</date>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>Creating extension functions</title>    
  <para>
   This chapter describes how to create your own library of XPath extension functions
   which can be called within your XSLT transformations.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Creating your extension functions</title>
    <para>
     The first step is to write the Eiffel code for your extension functions. You do this by writing at least one 
     Eiffel class. Usually you should create a separate class for each function, but if several functions are variations
     on a theme, it might be simpler for them all to share one class, and just use a different creation procedure
     for each implemented function. An example of this approach is the implementation of the core XPath functions
     fn:encode-for-uri(), fn:iri-to-uri() and fn:escape-html-uri(), which all share the same implementation code
     in XM_XPATH_ESCAPE_URI, the only difference between them being the set of reserved characters.
    </para>
    <para>
     Your Eiffel class should be a descendant of <classname>XM_XPATH_SYSTEM_FUNCTION</classname> (if it is possible for
     your function to always be evaluated when the transformation is compiled, then it is more efficient to inherit fron
     <classname>XM_XPATH_COMPILE_TIME_FUNCTION</classname> instead). 
    <warning>
     Writing extension functions as descendants of <classname>XM_XPATH_SYSTEM_FUNCTION</classname> probably requires some
     understanding of how the XPath library works. This is not properly documented yet. If in doubt ask for help on one of the Gobo
     mailing lists.
    </warning>
     You will usually
     want to redefine either <featurename>evaluate_item</featurename> or  <featurename>create_iterator</featurename>, or both
     (if your function ever returns sequences of more than one item, then you will need to redefine <featurename>create_iterator</featurename>).
    </para>
    <para>
     You may also need to redefine other routines. These routines are likely candidates:
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>pre_evaluate</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 By default, the library will attempt to pre-evaluate your function at compile time, if it can
	 determine that all the arguments are fixed values. If for some reason that is unsuitable behaviour, then
	 you should redefine this routine to do nothing.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>simplify</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This performs optimizations that do not depend upon the XPath static context. By
	 default it just simplifies all the other arguments. This is a suitable point for
	 setting optimization flags that depend upon the number of arguments actually passed.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>check_arguments</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine checks the number and type of arguments.
	 This is a suitable place for performing additional checks or optimizations on particular arguments.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>calculate_effective_boolean_value</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine evaluates the function as a boolean.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>check_static_type</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine performs static type checking on the function.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>optimize</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine performs optimizations at compile time. By default it optimizes
	 all the arguments.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>evaluate_as_string</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine evaluates the function when it is known to return a single string.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>compute_special_properties</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine sets flags for the optimization process.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>compute_intrinsic_dependencies</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine sets flags for the optimization process.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
     You will also need to implement the following routines:
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>item_type</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine tells the static type checker and optimizer what type of items might be returned by
	 the function. Be as specific as you can, so that more optimizations can be performed.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>required_type</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine tells the static type checker what type and length of sequence is allowed
	 for each argument.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>compute_cardinality</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This routine tells the static type checker and optimizer now many items might be returned by
	 the function.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
     You must also implement a creation routine with zero arguments. This <emphasis>must</emphasis> perform the following operations:
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Set the attributes <featurename>name</featurename> and <featurename>namespace_uri</featurename> to name
	your function.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Set <featurename>fingerprint</featurename> to match <featurename>name</featurename> and <featurename>namespace_uri</featurename>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Set the attributes <featurename>minimum_argument_count</featurename> and <featurename>maximum_argument_count</featurename> to 
	specify the number of permitted arguments.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Finally create <featurename>arguments</featurename> and set <featurename>initialized</featurename> to <featurename>True</featurename>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Creating an extension function library</title>
    <para>
     Next you should create a descendant of <classname>XM_XPATH_FUNCTION_LIBRARY</classname>. You need to implement two 
     routines:
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>is_function_available</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 If <featurename>a_fingerprint</featurename> is equal to the value of <featurename>fingerprint</featurename> for your function,
	 then you should return <featurename>True</featurename> if <featurename>an_arity</featurename> is -1, or if it lies (inclusively)
	 between the values that you set for <featurename>minimum_argument_count</featurename> and <featurename>maximum_argument_count</featurename>
	 for your function.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
       <term><featurename>bind_function</featurename></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 You should create the function that matches <featurename>a_fingerprint</featurename>.
	 Then call <featurecall><featurename>set_arguments</featurename><arguments><argument>some_arguments</argument></arguments></featurecall>.
	 Then you should set <featurename>last_bound_function</featurename> to the created function.
	</para>
	<para>
	  If the argument <featurename>is_restricted</featurename> is <featurename>True</featurename>, then your function is being
	  bound within an [xsl:]use-when context. If it is sensible for your function to be callable in such a context, then
	  by all means ignore this argument. Otherwise you should create an instance of <classname>XM_XSLT_DEFERRED_ERROR</classname>.
	  See <classname>XM_XSLT_BUILTIN_EXTENSION_FUNCTIONS</classname> for an example.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>     
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Informing the XSLT library of your extension function library</title>
    <para>
     There is one last step to take, you have to tell the library about the existence of your
     function library.
    </para>
    <para>
     Just pass your library as the sole argument to <featurename>add_extension_function_library</featurename>
     of <classname>XM_XSLT_CONFIGURATION</classname>. After this call, your library will be searched whenever
     a transformation is compiled.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
