<!--
	description:
	
		"XPointer"

	library: "Gobo Eiffel XPointer Library"
	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2005, Colin Adams and others"
	license: "Eiffel Forum License v2 (see forum.txt)"
	date: "$Date$"
	revision: "$Revision$"
-->

<chapterinfo>
  <copyright>
    <year>2005</year>
    <holder>Colin Adams and others</holder>
  </copyright>
  <author>
    <firstname>Colin</firstname>
    <surname>Adams</surname>
  </author>
  <email>colin@colina.demon.co.uk</email>
  <date>Friday, February 25th, 2005</date>
</chapterinfo>
<title>&title;</title>
<para>
  The XPath library includes an implementation of the &framework; and implementations for the W3C &xpointer; schemes
  <xpath>element</xpath> and <xpath>xmlns</xpath>. In addition, There is a &program_name_cased;-specific scheme: <xpath>&program_name;:xpath</xpath>.
</para> 
<section id="xpointer_framework">
  <title>Invoking the &framework;</title>
  <para>
    To invoke the &framework;, you must first create an instance of <classname>XM_XPOINTER_XPATH</classname>. This creates the &framework;, but
    no schemes are available - only <xpath>shorthand</xpath> pointers.
  </para>
  <para>
    The next step is to call <featurename>evaluate</featurename>. This takes two arguments. The second argument is the XML resource (well-formed document or external parsed entity, 
    represented as an <classname>XM_XPATH_DOCUMENT)</classname>. The first argument is the pointer represented as a <classname>STRING</classname>.
  </para>
  <para>
    The pointer should have no escaping, other than &xpointer; carat escaping, within it. So if you are starting with an <classname>UT_URI</classname>, simply calling 
    it's <featurename>fragment</featurename> routine is not sufficent. Instead, you should call the <featurename>fragment_item</featurename> routine, to
    get an <classname>UT_URI_STRING</classname>, and call that object's <featurename>decoded_utf8</featurename> (??? Is this right, Franck?).
  </para>
  <para>
    Calling <featurename>evaluate</featurename> will set <featurename>value</featurename> to a non-Void <classname>XM_XPATH_VALUE</classname>. If an &xpointer; error
    occured, then this object will have <featurename>value</featurename> set to an
    <classname>XM_XPATH_INVALID_VALUE</classname> in the case of an &framework; syntax error, or an <classname>XM_XPATH_EMPTY_SEQUENCE</classname> (marked in error) if 
    a <xpath>shorthand</xpath> pointer failed to locate any resources.
  </para>
  <para>
    &xpointer; schemes don't signal  &xpointer; errors - instead <featurename>value</featurename> will be set to an
    <classname>XM_XPATH_EMPTY_SEQUENCE</classname>.
  </para>
  <para>
    If a <xpath>shorthand</xpath> pointer, or an <xpath>element</xpath> scheme find a resource, then they set <featurename>value</featurename> to an
    <classname>XM_XPATH_SINGLETON_NODE</classname>. The <xpath>&program_name;:xpath</xpath> scheme sets <featurename>value</featurename> to an
    <classname>XM_XPATH_SEQUENCE_EXTENT</classname>, as it is possible for it to return any XPath sequence. 
  </para>
</section>
<section id="xpointer_schemes">
  <title>&xpointer; schemes</title>
  <para>
    If your pointer may contain anything other than a <xpath>shorthand</xpath> pointer, then you must configure the <classname>XM_XPOINTER_XPATH</classname>
    object with any schemes that you may wish to use. This is done by creating instances of descendants of <classname>XM_XPOINTER_XPATH_SCHEME</classname>,
    and passing them as the argument of <classname>XM_XPOINTER_XPATH</classname>'s <featurename>register_scheme</featurename> routine.
  </para>
  <para>
    Schemes provided in the library:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><classname>XM_XPOINTER_XPATH_XMLNS_SCHEME</classname></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The W3C <xpath>xmlns</xpath> scheme for defining namespace bindings.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><classname>XM_XPOINTER_XPATH_ELEMENT_SCHEME</classname></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The W3C <xpath>element</xpath> scheme for finding a single element via a <xpath>shorthand</xpath> pointer and/or by stepwise navigation.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><classname>XM_XPOINTER_XPATH_XPATH_SCHEME</classname></term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	  The  W3C <xpath>xpath2</xpath> scheme or the <xpath>&program_name;:xpath</xpath> schemes.
	</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>
</section>
<section id="xpointer_xpath_scheme">
  <title>The <xpath>&program_name;:xpath</xpath> scheme</title>
  <para>
    The &xpointer; scheme, which is an unapproved W3C working draft, is not implemented by this library.
    This is because:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  It uses XPath 1.0, whereas this library uses XPath 2.0. This means we could not make a compliant
	  implementation.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A lot of work is needed to extend XPath for this scheme.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The benefits compared with an XPath 2.0 scheme seem slim (only text-editing
	  applications are likely to see a clear benefit, and the implementations of the
	  XPath data model in this library are read-only).
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  It doesn't look likely that it will ever be approved.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    Instead, I have implemented a scheme which takes an XPath 2.0 expression as it's pointer. This has a local name of "xpath", and a namespace URI 
    of "http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/gexslt/extension". Therefore, you have to declare a prefix, using the <xpath>xmlns</xpath> scheme, before
    you can use this scheme.
  </para>
  <para>
    So, in order to find the third child of the document element, conditional upon it having an attribute named "test", then you will want a pointer that 
    looks something like: "xmlns(&program_name; = http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/gexslt/extension)&program_name;:xpath(/*[1]/*[3][@test]".
    <warning>
      Within a URI, the square brackets and spaces will need percent-encoding, so this example should actually read:
      "xmlns(&program_name;%20=%20http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/gexslt/extension)&program_name;:xpath(/*%5B1%5D/*%5B3%5D%5B@test%5D".
      although the spaces can always be omitted.
    </warning>
  </para>
  <para>
    Of course, if you want to use any namespace prefixes (other than "xml", which is always declared) within your XPath expression, then you will
    need to declare them also using further <xpath>xmlns</xpath> statements.
  </para>
  <para>
   Since writing the above documentation, the W3C have approved an identical scheme (I'm a trend-setter! :-), except (of course), it is in no namespace.
   It is also named xpath2 rather than xpath.
   Just call <featurename>make_w3c</featurename> instead of <featurename>make</featurename>. This is the recommended alternative, as it is much more
   portable, and it requires less typing in your URIs.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="xpointer_error_api">
  <title>The extended error API</title>
  <para>
    When you create the <classname>XM_XPOINTER_XPATH</classname>, the <featurename>make</featurename> procedure takes a single <classname>BOOLEAN</classname>
    argument. If you pass this as False, then you get the standard &framework; error reporting, as described above. If you instead set it to True, and if no
    resources were found, then <featurename>value</featurename> will be set to a value in error, as reported by the <emphasis>last</emphasis> scheme processor
    which detected a syntax or semantic error in it's scheme data.
  </para>
</section>
    

