<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
	description:

		"Unicode full case mappings"

	library: "Gobo Eiffel String Library"
	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2007, Colin Adams and others"
	license: "MIT License"
	date: "$Date$"
	revision: "$Revision$"
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/documentation" id="string/unicode/case">

<chapterinfo>
	<copyright>
		<year>2007</year>
		<holder>Colin Adams</holder>
	</copyright>
	<author>
		<firstname>Colin</firstname><surname>Adams</surname>
	</author>
	<email>colin-adams@users.sourceforge.net</email>
	<date>4 November 2007</date>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Unicode full case mappings</title>

<section>
<title>About full case mappings</title>

<para>
	Traditionally, <classname>STRING</classname> provides <featurename>as_lower</featurename> and <featurename>as_upper</featurename>
	for casing Latin-1 strings. The Gobo kernel library adds full Unicode versions in class <classname>UC_TYPE</classname> (and additionally
	a routine for providing a title-cased string. Title casing differs from upper casing the first character and lower-casing the rest, as some Unicode
	characters have a different form for title casing than for upper casing). However all these routines assume that strings don't change length
	under case mappings. This is not always true. For example, the german word &quot;e&#xdf;en&quot; (to eat) traditionally upper cases to &quot;ESSEN&quot;.
	The upper cased version is one character longer than the lower cased version.
</para>
	Except in legacy applications which expect strings not to change length, the traditional casing routines should not be used. Instead the full case mapping
	routines provided in this library should be used to get correct behaviour. Note that these casings are default mappings. The Unicode database provides additional
	locale-dependent and contextual forms (an example of the latter is final Greek sigma). These additional forms will be provided in the future on demand.
<para>
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>How to access the full case mapping routines provided by the library</title>

<para>
	The full case mapping routines provided by the library are defined in the deferred class 
	<classname>ST_UNICODE_CASE_MAPPING_INTERFACE</classname>. In order to gain access to these routines
	you can either inherit from <classname>ST_UNICODE_FULL_CASE_MAPPING</classname>, which
	provides information from the latest available version of unicode. Or you can inherit from a class
	for a particular version of Unicode (e.g. <classname>ST_UNICODE_V5000_FULL_CASE_MAPPING</classname> for Unicode version 5.0.0).
</para>

<para>
	Alternatively, you can access these classes as clients, by inheriting from <classname>ST_IMPORTED_UNICODE_FULL_CASE_MAPPING</classname> 
	or <classname>ST_IMPORTED_UNICODE_V500_FULL_CASE_MAPPING</classname>, which provide the routines
	<featurename>case_mapping</featurename> and <featurename>case_mapping_v500</featurename> respectively.
</para>

<para>
	The latter method is necessary if you want to be able to use full case mappings from two different versions of Unicode within
	the same class.
</para>

</section>

</chapter>
