<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
	description:

		"Unicode normalization routines"

	library: "Gobo Eiffel String Library"
	copyright: "Copyright (c) 2005, Colin Adams and others"
	license: "Eiffel Forum License v2 (see forum.txt)"
	date: "$Date$"
	revision: "$Revision$"
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://www.gobosoft.com/eiffel/gobo/documentation" id="string/unicode/about">

<chapterinfo>
	<copyright>
		<year>2005</year>
		<holder>Colin Adams</holder>
	</copyright>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Colin</firstname><surname>Adams</surname>
	</author>
	<email>colin-adams@users.sourceforge.net</email>
	<date>4 November 2005</date>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Unicode normalization routines provided by the library</title>
<section>
  <title>Which class to choose</title>
  <para>
    You have the choice of using the latest version of Unicode that
    is supported by the library, or you can choose a specific version.
  </para>
  <para>
    You have the choice of inheriting the routines, or using them as
    a client object. The latter is the only way to use more than one version of 
    Unicode within a class, although this seems an unlikely requirement.
  </para>
  <para>
    At the time I write this documentation, 4.1.0 is the latest version of
    Unicode, and it is also the latest and only version supported by this library.
    But 5.0.0 is currently in beta. So for the purposes of illustration, I shall assume
    that 5.0.0 is now live, and that this library supports it.
    Do you could inherit from one of the following:

    <variablelist>
 
      <varlistentry>
	<term>ST_UNICODE_NORMALIZATION_ROUTINES</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    This would give you direct access to routines for version 5.0.0 of Unicode,
	    but when 5.1.0 was supported by the library, you would then get the 5.1.0 routines.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>ST_UNICODE_V500_NORMALIZATION_ROUTINES</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    This would also give you direct access to routines for version 5.0.0 of Unicode,
	    but this would not change, even when the library was updated to support 5.1.0.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>ST_UNICODE_V410_NORMALIZATION_ROUTINES</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    This would give you direct access to routines for version 4.1.0 of Unicode,
	    and this would not change, even when the library was updated.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>ST_UNICODE_IMPORTED_NORMALIZATION_ROUTINES</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    This would give you indirect access to routines for version 5.0.0 of Unicode, via
	    <featurename>normalization</featurename>,
	    but when 5.1.0 was supported by the library, you would then get indirect access 
	    to the 5.1.0 routines via the same feature.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
	<term>ST_UNICODE_V500_IMPORTED_NORMALIZATION_ROUTINES</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    This would give you indirect access to routines for version 5.0.0 of Unicode, via
	    <featurename>normalization_v500</featurename>,
	    but this would not change, even when the library was updated to support 5.1.0.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>ST_UNICODE_V410_IMPORTED_NORMALIZATION_ROUTINES</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    This would give you indirect access to routines for version 4.1.0 of Unicode, via
	    <featurename>normalization_v410</featurename>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
    </variablelist>

  </para>

  <para>
    To use routines from both 5.0.0 and 4.1.0 versions of Unicode, you would import both of the
    last two classes in the preceding list.
  </para>

</section>

<section>
  <title>The routines provided by the library</title>

  <para>
    All these classes provide access to the same set of routines, via inheritance from
    <classname>ST_UNICODE_NORMALIZATION_INTERFACE</classname>. Note that ASCII and Latin-1
    <classname>STRING</classname>s can be passed to all of these routines, as well as  
    <classname>UC_UTF8_STRING</classname>s, as they all operate on code-points, accessed via the <featurename>item_code</featurename>
    feature. By design, Unicode allocates the same code points to Latin-1 characters as the
    ISO-8859-1 encoding does. Thus we keep compatibility.
  </para>

  <para>
    The following routines are available to check if a <classname>STRING</classname> is
    in the desired normalization form:
   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><featurename>is_nfd_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): BOOLEAN</featurename></listitem>
     <listitem><featurename>is_nfkd_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): BOOLEAN</featurename></listitem>
     <listitem><featurename>is_nfc_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): BOOLEAN</featurename></listitem>
     <listitem><featurename>is_nfkc_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): BOOLEAN</featurename></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
    The following routines do not assume anything about the current normalization state of their argument.
    If the argument is already in the desired normalization form, then the original object will be returned.
    Otherwise a new object will be allocated and returned:
  <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><featurename>as_nfd_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): STRING</featurename></listitem>
     <listitem><featurename>as_nfkd_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): STRING</featurename></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
    The following routines require that their argument is <emphasis>not</emphasis> in the required normalization
    form, and always allocate and return a new object:
  <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><featurename>to_nfd_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): STRING</featurename></listitem>
     <listitem><featurename>to_nfkd_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): STRING</featurename></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
    So when you desire to work with a decomposed form:
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem><para>If you know that your string is in the desired form, do nothing </para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>
       If you know that your string is <emphasis>not</emphasis> in the desired form,
       call <featurename>to_nfd_normalized_string</featurename> or <featurename>to_nfkd_normalized_string</featurename></para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem><para>
       Otherwise, call <featurename>as_nfd_normalized_string</featurename> or <featurename>as_nfkd_normalized_string</featurename>.
       You can then test for object identity, if you wish to know whether normalization was actually required.</para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
    The composing routines always allocate and return a new object, irrespective of the status of the argument::
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><featurename>to_nfc_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): STRING</featurename></listitem>
      <listitem><featurename>to_nfkc_normalized_string (a_source: STRING): STRING</featurename></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

 <para>
   The Unicode Character Database tabulates a lot of properties for each code-point. Some of these are relevant for
   the normalization process. There are three that in some circumstances might be of interest to an application. They are:
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><featurename>canonical_combining_class_property (a_code_point: INTEGER): INTEGER</featurename></listitem>
      <listitem><featurename>decomposition_type_property (a_code_point: INTEGER): INTEGER</featurename></listitem>
      <listitem><featurename>decomposition_mapping_property (a_code_point: INTEGER): DS_ARRAYED_LIST [INTEGER]</featurename></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
 </para>

 <para>
    The canonical combining class determines how different parts of a character are overlayed when
    displayed. 
 </para>

 <para>
    The decomposition mapping lists the code-points in the decomposition of a code-point. The decomposition type
    indicates whether a code point has a canonical decomposition, or if not, what <emphasis>type</emphasis> of
    compatibility decomposition it has. The results of this routine are available as symbolic constants in 
    <classname>UC_UNICODE_CONSTANTS</classname>. Note that if a code-point has no decomposition, then the result of
    this routine will be <featurename>Canonical_decomposition_mapping</featurename>, so you must check
    for a non-Void result from <featurename>decomposition_mapping_property</featurename> to confirm that
    a code-point actually has a canonical decomposition.
 </para>

</section>

</chapter>
